בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף ק', daf kuf,
100. Very short דף, daf, a lot of דקדוקים, dikdukaim, so we're
behind. God willing, we shall catch up today. So we pick up
on צ"ט עמוד ב' Tzadi Tet amud beis and we are
אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. It is four lines before the lines begin
to get wide. First word on the line is אומן, uman, actually
five lines before the beginning of שמואל. Shmuel. So five lines before
the lines get wide on צ"ט עמוד ב', Tzadi Tet amud beis,
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, טבח אומן, Tabach uman, you have an expert
butcher שקלקל shekalkel and he, he made a mistake. Here we're dealing
with sort of essentially malpractice, you know, שחיטה, shechitah, שחיטה, shechitah, yeah,
he ruined your $2,000 animal. He שחט shechted it and he slipped.
It wasn't a טריפה, treifah, he slipped. חייב לשלם, chayav l'shaleim, he
has to pay. Now we are finally getting back to the משנה
mishnah because you remember the משנה mishnah said you gave אומנין umnin
something to fix and they ruined it, you know, or a builder
something to fix and he ruined it, he has to pay. So
the question is, so we had a whole discussion about whether he
owns the improvement before he's given it to you and does he
have to pay for the base or does he have to pay
even for what he improved? Okay, but now returning to the real
focus of the משנה mishnah and the question, the key question the
משנה mishnah never addressed, just said, oh, you know, if a craftsman
ruins it he has to pay. Well, was he negligent or not
negligent? How do you assess negligence, right? So now we're going to
finally start to deal with that. So he says if an expert,
now the reason he emphasizes expert, which is not clear in the
משנה, mishnah, although you might imagine that anybody who's doing this trade
and anybody who's putting their hand on a $10,000 animal knows what
they're doing, but the more it's emphasized that this person is an
expert, then the more you should assume that anything that happens is
like a freak event, right? I mean, nobody is perfect, right? So
but if you have somebody who's a real, you know, has a
lot of experience, a real expert or whatever, there should be a
general presumption that he wasn't negligent, you know, doesn't mean that there's
not a slip, but that could happen without negligence. But he says
no. So let's take a look. So he says אומן שטבח שקלקל
חייב לשלם, Uman shetabach shekalkel chayav l'shaleim, he
is חייב, chayav, I don't care that he's an אומן, uman, okay,
that he's an expert. מזיק הוא פושע הוא, Mazik hu posheia hu,
he's a מזיק, mazik, he was negligent. Can't say it was an
accident, it was an act of God. אנס קמאי לא שחט לי
מכאן ושחט לי מכאן, Anas koimei lo shechat li mikan ve-shechat li
mikan, you can't say, oh, I was just doing what the בעל
הבית ba'al habayis asked. No, he asked you to do it correctly.
It's as if he said שחט, shecht, you know, as if he
asked you to שחט shecht from the neck and you שחט shechted
from the back of the neck. Just because you were under the
instruction of the בעל הבית ba'al habayis doesn't mean that when you
make a mistake you're doing his bidding. So you're negligent, you have
to pay. So the key point though here is there's two questions
that we're going to be dealing with. Question number one is what
is required to make somebody liable to pay? Do you need negligence
or do we say like an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, why do
you need negligence? You destroyed my object, you know, before we said
that even if you're an אונס oness you have to pay. So
one is what's
needed, is negligence needed. The other is assessing whether it was present
or not. So שמואל Shmuel here says both. You need negligence and
we should assume that when there was a trip up that it
was due to negligence even if the guy's an expert. All right,
so that's שמואל's Shmuel's statement. So now the גמרא Gemara says למה
לי למימר מזיק הוא פושע הוא? Lama lei leimemar mazik hu posheia
hu? Why did he have to say he's a מזיק, mazik, he's
a פושע? posheia? Just say he's a מזיק. mazik. No, אי אמר
מזיק הוא, ei amar mazik hu, if he had just said he's
a מזיק, mazik, הוי אמינא הני מילי היכא דעביד בשכר, havi amina
hanei milei heicha de-avid besachar, maybe that means that it's not gross
negligence, maybe that's only if you pay him. Meaning, the more that
he's an expert, right, the more that you should assume that a
mistake that happens is not due to negligence. That's on the one
hand. On the other hand, the more that you pay him, the
more it heightens his degree of responsibility. Doesn't make him any more
expert, it makes him more responsible. It should lower the threshold of
what you need in order to be liable. Okay, you're being paid,
that creates an added responsibility. Now one way of framing this is,
I give you my object and I'm paying you, you're a שומר
שכר. shomer sachar. But it doesn't seem like we're being paid because
he's a שומר, shomer, right, as a guardian, that he's חייב chayav
because he's a מזיק. mazik. But nevertheless, the degree of care he
has to demonstrate while dealing with the animal, dealing with the object
you gave him, the more you pay him, the higher degree of
responsibility. So if he had just said he's a מזיק, mazik, I
might have said well, okay, he's not negligent, but if he's being
paid he has a higher degree of responsibility. Okay, I would have
said היכא דעביד בשכר, heicha de-avid besachar, if he's doing it with
a fee, then maybe, you know, he's maybe not an אונס oness
but he's not a פושע, posheia, maybe he's somewhere in the middle,
and if you're paying him then he's liable. אבל היכא דעביד בחינם,
aval heicha de-avid bechinam,
if he's doing it for free, so
לא, lo, I would say in that case no. He doesn't have
high degree of responsibility, and he only would be חייב chayav if
he's negligent, and maybe I should assume he's not negligent, he is
an expert after all. קא משמע לן פושע הוא. Ka mashma lan
poshea hu. No, I'm sorry, I consider that to be, שמואל Shmuel
says I consider any trip up, any mistake to be negligent. Now,
one does wonder, is it negligent because genuinely like as the act
I was doing this, I was somehow distracted or being sloppy? Or
is somehow the negligence part of the fact that I am, you
know, because I'm in the trade and because I am agreeing to
do the job, you know, sort of what defines negligence and the
degree of like of care that I have to demonstrate, you know,
just makes even smaller things, you know, within that context considered negligent?
Like, you know, I mean if you've got a doctor who's doing
surgery and doing an operation, right, I mean what it would require
for me to be negligent to try to do a surgery would
be to pick up a scalpel. Okay. But what it would require
for a doctor, even a tiny thing, I said 2 ccs and
I meant 0.2 ccs, well, excuse me, that's like gross negligent for
somebody who is a professional doctor, right? So the definition of negligence,
the same way the threshold can, you know, change if I'm paying
him, the threshold can change if you're an expert and you're dealing
with something that's, you know, $2,000 cow, you're dealing with a human
life, you know, that could change the definition of what's considered to
be negligent. But שמואל Shmuel hasn't said any of that. All he
said is, you know, I don't care that you're an expert and
I don't care that you weren't being paid, this is a negligent
and you're liable to pay.
We have that dynamic and sort of
transparencies around risk, you know, oh, you want me to שחט shecht
this bull? Well, I just want you to know, he's got a
particularly thick neck, so the chances that I might not actually do
the שחיטה shechita properly is a little bit higher, so I just
want you to know. Do you still want me to go?
Right, so I'm sure if you said that, that would exculpate.
That's
a good point, right.
Right, if you said I'm doing this operation, but you should know
there's a heightened risk of
infection, do you
still want me to do it?
Right, right, right. So then all of a sudden, that's a very
good point, right, so like way to to inform somebody of the
risks and have the person assume the risk. Right, that's a very
good point which has not being sort of discussed
yet. Right, right, right, that is a good point. Now, the other
thing that I want to say is, as we continue this, is
since you're dealing with an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, why do you
need to talk about the fact that he's פושע? poshea? Who cares
whether he's פושע poshea or not? He took my beautiful cow and
he turned it into a piece of נבילה, neveila, right? So I
think I might have to take this, this might be my son's.
Okay, so the question is, why do you need him to be
פושע? poshea? He's an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. He destroyed this gorgeous
cow and he made it a worthless piece of meat, right? He
didn't make it כשר kosher meat. That's just an אדם המזיק. adam
hamazik. The משנה mishna when it says that you give it to
somebody to fix your box and he breaks it, he pays, doesn't
say that he has to be negligent. So why is negligent needed?
So you might remember that there was a debate from many months
ago, I don't know many months, two three months ago, רמב"ן Ramban
and תוספות, Tosafot, whether when the גמרא Gemara says אדם מועד לעולם
adam muad l'olam even in a case of אונס, ones, whether the
גמרא Gemara really meant it or not. תוספות Tosafot says the גמרא
Gemara doesn't really mean it. You're not חייב chayav as an אדם
המזיק adam hamazik unless there's a degree of negligence, right? There's a
there's a continuum. There's complete act of God, אונס, ones, there's complete
negligence, and then there's this case in the middle called like גניבה
ואבידה, geneiva va'aveida, you know, not gross negligence, but not a complete
accident, not a complete like, you know, you know, out of your
control type of a thing. And תוספות Tosafot says to be חייב
chayav for an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, you need at least a
certain degree of negligence. You don't need gross negligence, but a certain
degree. And one of the proofs he brings is the סוגיא sugya
we're in the middle of. Because the סוגיא sugya we're in the
middle of consistently discusses do you consider this guy to be negligent
or not? So תוספות Tosafot says why do you need that if
an אדם adam is really מועד לעולם, muad l'olam, then it shouldn't
matter if he's negligent. רמב"ן Ramban disagrees. If you might remember, the
רמב"ן Ramban says most of the cases that תוספות Tosafot brings to
prove that you need negligence, like the תוספות's Tosafot's example is is
that if you're asleep and I lie down and sleep next to
you and you injure me in your sleep, you're exempt, right? Remember
that? So the תוספות Tosafot says ah, you see, you do need
negligence because you injured me and you're exempt. So the רמב"ן Ramban
says most of those cases, the issue was פשיעת הניזק. pshia hanizak.
The person who is damaged was themselves negligent. What the heck are
you doing lying down next to a guy who's asleep? Okay. But
how about this case? This case, right, why does the שוחט shochet
need negligence to be חייב chayav if it really is the truth
that אדם מועד לעולם? adam muad l'olam? Right? That's the question that
תוספות Tosafot asks. So the רמב"ן Ramban answers this in four words,
maybe five words. What the רמב"ן Ramban says, אין באומן הטועה במלאכתו
משום מזיק. ein b'uman hattoeh bimlachto mishum mazik. I don't know, we
can count the words. אין באומן הטועה במלאכתו משום מזיק, ein b'uman
hattoeh bimlachto mishum mazik, or משום אדם המזיק, mishum adam hamazik, five,
six, or seven words. That's his whole answer to this. A a
craftsman that makes a mistake is not an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik.
Even if he breaks the box, and even if he, you know,
even if he turns this cow into a נבילה, neveila, you can't
classify that as an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. Which basically means, you
know, yes, is it true that he did an act to the
object and the object was destroyed? Sure. But an אדם המזיק... adam
hamazik... fundamentally starts by the fact that I had no right to
be to be doing something to your object, right? I was sort
of invading your body, your property, your space. Like that's a מזיק.
mazik. Okay? That defines me as a מזיק mazik and then even
if it was by accident, רמב"ן Ramban says a wind picks me
up and threw me down on
your picture and it broke on your iPhone and it broke, nevertheless,
I wasn't there with permission. I wasn't necessarily a רשע, rasha, right?
A wind pushed me on it, but the fact that I was
I was encountering your property without permission, that defines me as a
מזיק. mazik. And then we say אדם מועד לעולם. adam mu'ad l'olam.
But the fact here that you gave me the task to שחט
shecht your animal, to fix your box, even if I wind up
breaking it, you can't call me a מזיק, mazik, right? You can
call me like that you would sue me for like professional negligence,
right? That's what you would sue me for, for malpractice. But fundamentally,
my relationship to you and my relationship to this object is not
one—I assume if I intentionally say, great, he gave me his car,
now I'm going to wreck it, okay? The intention would define me,
but as long as I am trying to do the task you
assigned me, then the רמב"ן Ramban says you cannot call that מזיק.
mazik. So what are you calling it? Is it a שומר? shomer?
Is it some other definition? Is it once you're negligent then that
makes you like you do have כוונה? kavana? Maybe that's a way
of saying it. Until I'm not negligent then I'm just doing what
you asked and even if it broke, I'm not a מזיק. mazik.
But as soon as I'm negligent, then I'm acting outside
of my sort of mission, outside of my agency, and then I
am a מזיק. mazik. The same way if I had כוונה kavana
I would become a מזיק. mazik. Okay? But the רמב"ן Ramban says
the base here is your relationship to me and the object is
that you have the right to be doing something with this object
and you're not a מזיק mazik and that's why we need פשיעה
p'shia in order even in order to make you liable. Yes.
So it sounds a lot like the conversation about if you allow
someone to come into your courtyard and then they break your pots
or something.
Right,
so exactly. You let them in their in your domain, right, exactly
that thing. Exactly. And there there's questions, right? It could be once
I let them into my domain not only are they not liable
for things they do wrong but I assume liability for them. Right.
So yes. Exactly. So again he doesn't spell out what the mechanism
is that once you're פושע poshe'ah the guy is חייב. chayav. Is
he חייב chayav of a special הלכה halacha called called malpractice of
אומנים? umnim? We've never heard that הלכה. halacha. Is he a שומר?
shomer? My guess would be that once he's פושע poshe'ah it's like
he has כוונה. kavana. You could give me your cow, if I
intentionally make it a נבילה, neveila, I'm a מזיק. mazik. So if
I'm פושע poshe'ah I'm a מזיק. mazik. But as long as I'm
not פושע poshe'ah I'm an אומן, uman, I'm not a מזיק. mazik.
Yes.
So that tension between מזיק mazik and פשיעה p'shia is I understand
that but then how do we reconcile the אדם מועד לעולם? adam
mu'ad l'olam?
Well, that's what he says. אדם מועד לעולם adam mu'ad l'olam is
if we categorize you as a מזיק, mazik, then we say, it's
like which part of שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch do we look this
up in, right? Here an אומן uman broke the thing. Do we
say, sorry, let me get down my שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and
look up הלכות מזיק Hilchos Mazik or let me get down my
שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and look up הלכות אומנים? Hilchos Umnim? Okay?
If I'm going to get down my—if I see this as
you are a destroyer of this person's object, you destroyed it, right,
then then I'll say, oh, then it doesn't matter whether you were
negligent or not. But if my fundamental lens to bring to this
is an אומן uman who made a mistake, then I don't pull
down הלכות מזיק. Hilchos Mazik. Okay?
Why do you have to say אונס? oness? Why can't there be
some state where you're saying it's some—if a person damages something they're
either a מזיק mazik or
פשיעה. p'shia.
There's no—No, because if I don't have the right to be handling
it, if I don't have this
פרשת אומנים, parshas umnim, if I—if a—the רמב"ן's Ramban example is a
wind could come and push me down and I would break your
thing and I have to pay you. So you have to underscore
that there was absolutely no negligence there, I was a total אונס
oness and I still have to pay you. That's אדם מועד לעולם.
adam mu'ad l'olam. But that's if you're in the category of מזיק.
mazik. If you're in the category of violating this person's property, not
out of any fault, but you don't fundamentally—are you're not fundamentally have
a different role regarding this property. A similar question would be if
I'm a שומר, shomer, and this is a little bit ironic, okay,
but this is a discussion in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, which is
you give me your barrels to watch, okay, of wine. And here
I am, and one of the things I have to do is
I have to, like, you know, move them around and transport them.
And there I am, or maybe I'm not watching them, I don't
know, maybe you're hiring me to move them. But let's even say
you're hiring me to watch it, but part of my responsibility of
watching it is, you know, I move it and then I have
to sweep behind it and in my process of moving it I
break it, okay. But let's say we decided that I was an
אונס, oness, okay? Am I פטור patur because I'm a שומר shomer
who was an אונס, oness, or am I חייב chayav because I'm
an אדם המזיק? adam hamazik? And the רמב"ן Ramban says you're פטור
patur because you were a שומר shomer who was an אונס. oness.
And that's almost ironic. I was a שומר, shomer, so I accepted
responsibility for the object, but at the same time I accepted responsibility,
I had a right to be handling the object, and the fact
that I had a right to be handling— putting the object puts
me in a category of שומרים *shomrim*, and anything that happens I
have to look up הלכות שומרים *hilchos shomrim*, or puts me in
a category of אומן uman *uman*, and anything that happens I have
to look up הלכות אומן *hilchos uman*, right? So a מזיק mazik
*mazik* is when I don't have a right to be handling that
object. Yeah.
It's very interesting that when you frame it that way that I
have a right to be handling this animal because I'm the אומן
*uman* or I'm the שומר *shomer*. Right. You didn't use the word
ownership, but it comes close to that for that moment, for that
task, in a way it's mine.
Yeah, I wouldn't go that
far though. Right. I mean, right, you're not violating this person's, you
know, right. That's what I think it is. I think it starts
with the fact that you're not violating, you know. You could violate
sometimes not due to your fault. Again, you could be put, you
know, a wind could push you down, but there was a violation
there that makes you a מזיק mazik, *mazik*.
Rabbi, what were you going to add? I think it's in the
Moats v. Falgas, I think, you know, Lori says this is in
Greenstein, I didn't mean to stab him, I tripped and my knife...
But there you go.
27 times. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Alright. Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay,
איתיביה רב חמא *Eisivei Rav Chama*, I have to keep to my
promise that we're going to catch up today. That was too much
fun right there. איתיביה *Eisivei*, but it was so important to lay
that out. Okay, second wide line here. איתיביה רב חמא בר גוריא
לשמואל *Eisivei Rav Chama bar Guria l'Shmuel*. רב חמא בר גוריא *Rav
Chama bar Guria* challenged שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* who said that this שוחט
shoichet *shochet* is a פושע *poshea*. הנותן בהמה לטבח ונבלה *Hanosein beheima
l'tabach venivla*. So if you give an animal to a שוחט shoichet
*shochet* and it becomes a נבלה *neveilah*, he slipped, meaning it wasn't
a טריפה *treifa*, he actually slipped somehow. Okay, אומן פטור הדיוט hedyot,
חייב chayav *uman patur hedyot chayav*. If he's an אומן *uman* he's
פטור *patur*, so then we assume that it was a freak thing.
If he's a non-expert, I don't know what you're doing giving a
non-expert your animal, but anyway then we assume that it was negligence.
ואם נושא שכר בין אומן בין הדיוט hedyot חייב chayav *v'im nosei
sachar bein uman bein hedyot chayav*. And if you're paying the guy,
whether אומן *uman* or הדיוט hedyot. *hedyot* you're חייב chayav *chayav*. So
this disagrees with שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* both ways. Number one, that an
אומן *uman* fundamentally is פטור *patur*, and number two, that paying money,
you know, is makes a difference. Okay, so anyway, but you see
that fundamentally he says an אומן *uman* is פטור *patur* where שמואל
Shmuel *Shmuel* says fundamentally an אומן *uman* is חייב chayav, *chayav*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר ליה *amar lei*, he said back
to him, לאחר מוחא אתא *le'achar mocha ata*?
Is this rabbi who's coming to ask this question... wait a minute...
אטו מן דרבנן *atu man d'rabbanan*?
Is this rabbi coming to like, you know, cloud your mind? So...
wait a minute, I'm just trying to remember how to put in
the punctuation here...
Oh no, אטו מן דרבנן *atu man d'rabbanan* comes after, I'm sorry.
So אמר ליה לאחר מוחא *amar lei le'achar mocha*. You're coming to
like cloud your mind. Like that's a stupid question, which is not
so helpful. It seems like a pretty good question. אתו מן דרבנן
*asu man d'rabbanan*, so another one of the rabbis came, קמותיב ליה
*kamosiv lei* and asked the same question from the same ברייתא braita.
*beraisa* to challenge שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*. אמר ליה *amar lei*,
so שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* said to him, הא דשקלת מאי דשקל חברך
*ha d'shakalta mai d'shakal chavrach*. So now, you know, that insult I
gave your friend, now you should take that insult. Okay, that's a
good way of dealing with challenges, just insult the people who ask
them. Okay, קאמינא לכון אנא רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *ka'amina lachon ana
Rabbi Meir*. Now we're going to see why he thinks it's a
stupid question. קאמינא לכון אנא רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *ka'amina lachon ana
Rabbi Meir*, I was dealing within a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi
Meir* position to say that you're negligent and you have to pay.
וקא מותיתו לי רבנן Rabbanan. *v'ka musisu li Rabbanan*? You're telling me
a ברייתא *beraisa* that follows a different approach, follows the רבנן Rabbanan
*Rabbanan's* approach. אמאי לא דייקיתו מילי *amai lo daykis u'mili*? Why weren't
you paying closer attention to my words? שאני אומר מזיק mazik, הוא
פושע הוא נעשה כאומר לו שחוט לי מכאן ושחט לי מכאן *she'ani
omer mazik hu poshea hu na'aseh k'omer lo shechot li mikan v'shachat
li mikan*. Because I was very clear what my reasoning was. I
said the guy's a מזיק *mazik* and he's a פושע *poshea*, you're
acting outside of your license, it's because when you make a mistake
it's like you שחט shecht *shechted* in the wrong place. So what
should I have figured, what should you have figured from my framing
it that way? מאן אית ליה האי סברא רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*man is lei hai sevara Rabbi Meir*? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi
Meir* is the one who says that when people slip up they're
a פושע *poshea*. By saying he's a פושע *poshea* and I say
that I treat a slip-up as a פושע *poshea*, you should have
realized that this was a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* position.
Which רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* we'll see in a minute.
So it was you were being stupid for not paying attention and
not figuring out that I was talking according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*. So דאמר רבי מאיר *d'amar Rabbi Meir* says, מיבעי ליה למימר
מאנפיה *mibaiya lei l'meimar m'anpei*. You should... it's your responsibility to sort
of watch over yourself and be careful that you don't make slips.
For רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* slips are not accidents, accidents don't just
happen. Okay? Accidents happen because you're not being careful enough, and therefore
anybody who slips is a פושע *poshea*. That's who I'm talking about.
I'm adopting רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. Okay, now which רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הי רבי מאיר *hei Rabbi
Meir*? Where does רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* say this? אילימא האי רבי
מאיר *eileima hai Rabbi Meir* the following רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* דתנן
Detnan, *d'snan*. קשר בעליו במוסירה ונעל בפניו כראוי ויצא והזיק *kashar ba'alav
b'mosira v'na'al b'fanav k'ra'uy v'yatza v'hizik*. Now we get to do a
little חזרה *chazara* on the first half of בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*.
If the owner tied up the animal with a rope and it
went out and it damaged, this goring ox, בין תם בין מועד
חייב chayav *bein tam bein muad chayav*, you're liable whether it is
a תם *tam* or a מועד *muad*. דברי רבי מאיר *divrei Rabbi
Meir*. So you see רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, even if you did
a שמירה shemirah *shmira*, you're חייב chayav *chayav*. So maybe that shows
you you have a high degree of responsibility. No, that's not about
slipping... And that's not about your own acts. התם בקראי פליגי, that's
a debate of how to read the פסוקים, psukim, what level of
שמירה is good for a שור. shor. You know, that's not related
to our discussion. אלא הא רבי מאיר, Ela ha Rabbi Meir, the
following רבי מאיר. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה, mishna, צבעו
לו אדום וצבעו שחור, tzva'o lo adom v'tzva'o shachor, we're going to
come up to this, שחור וצבעו אדום. shachor v'tzva'o adom. You gave
it to the dyer to dye red, he dyed black; black, and
he dyed red. רבי מאיר אומר נותן לו דמי צמרו, Rabbi Meir
omer noten lo dmei tzmoro, you are considered to have been a
מזיק to his wool and you have to pay him for his
wool. So that seems a little relevant because there actually, you know,
he's you're making a mistake in your job and you're ruining the
thing. So the גמרא Gemara says: No. התם בידיים כלו מיניה. Hasam
beyadayim kalu minei. There, with directly with your hands you've burnt it
up, you've destroyed it. Meaning what does it mean? It means that
it's sort of it seems to be there's a difference between if
I'm doing a שחיטה shechitah and I slip or if I fundamentally,
it's like when you cut off, you know, I mean they have
these terrible stories of doctors sometimes they cut off the wrong leg,
you know. So it's like if you put the thing in the
wrong dye that's not like in the process there was a little
bit of a twitch, right? That was like fundamentally you did the
wrong
thing. Okay, that's בידיים כלו מיניה. beyadayim kalu minei. Now רש"י Rashi
says, רש"י Rashi is a little bothered with this but he gives
a different explanation. רש"י Rashi says שנתכוון לשנות. shenitkaven l'shanot. רש"י Rashi
says: I know you told me red but I think black would
look a lot better on this wool. Okay, now that's very much
limiting that case. I still think that there could be a case.
It's also בידיים, beyadayim, that's the problem that רש"י... Rashi...
I know, I know. So he's throwing in כוונה. kavanah. But that's
I think that's a little bit too limiting it. I think I
think that you could make a distinction between there's a type of
like a ניתקא, nitka, a slippage, and there's a type of really
doing something else. When שמואל says: It's like I said שחטיה shechtiyah
and you שחטת shechtet there, it means it should be obvious to
everybody that if rather than שחיטה shechting on the neck you שחטת
shechtet a wrong part of the body, nobody would debate that's negligence,
right? So if instead of dyeing it red you dyed it black,
nobody would debate that's negligence, you did a fundamentally different thing. The
question here is if you slipped in the process of what you
were doing when you were supposed to be doing.
Yes. Another question is is that also negligence?
Is that also negligence? And do we say that a person has
a responsibility to be so watching over themselves that they don't even
do slips? Okay.
So, right, but it's not the same thing. You can't compare like
I put in a personal order I want this dyed red you
dyed blue and you say you know I'm telling you everyone's gonna
love it blue. There's a difference between that and שחט like it's
a ritual thing like there's rules for how to...
Yeah, I don't maybe, but I mean the rule, you know, whatever,
I'm not sure the ritual makes the difference. I think the difference
is is like if I say, yeah, I dyed it blue but
slip ups happen, right? That's what, what do you mean slip ups
happen? How could you, I wrote it on the sheet, it said
red, right? That's not a slip up. Right, if it said yeah
you know whatever you know a little bit it burnt, sometimes things
burn a little bit in the process, you know, again you might
still want to be reimbursed but that's a little of a different
quality. And that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. We're talking here
about slip ups, we're not talking about fundamental changes. Okay, אלא הא
רבי מאיר, Ela ha Rabbi Meir, the following רבי מאיר. דתנן, we
taught in the משנה: mishna: נשבר כדו ולא סילקה, Nishbar kado v'lo
silka, נתקלה גמלו ולא העמידה. nitkala gamlo v'lo hemida. If your pitcher
broke and you didn't remove it and the shards are there in
the middle of the street, or your camel fell and you didn't
get it to stand up and then somebody came and they tripped
on it and hurt themselves. Is it your בור? bor? Did you
make this בור bor with negligence? Is the fact that you have
broken shards, is that considered to have been an act of negligence
on your part? So רבי מאיר אומר חייב בניזקא, Rabbi Meir omer
chayav binizka, you are חייב chayav if they do damage. וחכמים אומרים
פטור מדיני אדם וחייב מדיני שמיים. V'chachamim omrim patur midinei adam v'chayav
midinei shamayim. No, you're exempt in human court, only חייב chayav in
heavenly court. וקיימא לן, V'kayma lan, and we have when we worked
through this whole case much earlier in the מסכת, masechta, we concluded
בניתקא פושע הוא פליגי. benitka poshea hu paleigi. The debate is whether
you consider I slipped and I tripped and I broke my pot,
is that an act of negligence or is that an accident? Right,
that's the old question. Accidents don't just happen, right? So רבי מאיר
says when you slip and trip I consider that to be negligence.
I consider that you have responsibility to watch where you're going and
to watch what you're doing. So now of course we could all
make a big difference, right? There are people who trip over their
own two feet on a flat type of a surface and they're
completely distracted not watching where they're going and there's the type of
a thing when I'm שחיטה shechting and all of a sudden I
got like a little twitch, right? You can't control an involuntary twitch,
right? You know there are different degrees of slip ups, okay, but
nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is putting it all in the same category
and saying שמואל says this guy could be an expert, he could
completely have known what he was doing, there's no such thing as
accidents. Any slip is because you weren't being careful enough. Okay.
Yes, but couldn't you say in this case there was a question
of indirect damage, the camel or the shards on the road?
Yeah, but but there the גמרא Gemara says the question is whether
you're considered to be have made a בור. bor. Whether you know
and if you make you can only have made a בור bor
if the thing is considered to have fallen due to your negligence.
Okay. So you're right, it's not an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, but
it's still a question of judging is there such a thing as
an accident. And רבי מאיר says there are no accidents. Okay, so
now I mean unless somebody else does it to you. But something
that you do
yourself... All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so that's
the issue. We all agree that the שוחט shoichet needs negligence, and
the question is do we define it as negligence or not? אמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabba bar Bar Chana
amar Rabbi Yochanan טבח אומן שקלקל חייב, tabbach umman shekilkal chayav, so
if an expert שוחט shoichet, ruins the animal, he's חייב chayav ואפילו
הוא אומן, va'afilu hu umman, even if he's an expert like שמואל
כטבחי ציפורי, ketabbachei tzipori, even if he's like the most expert שוחט
shoichet in the world, like the שוחטים shochtim of ציפורי, Tzipori, they
were expert שוחטים. shochtim. I agree like שמואל, no such thing as
an accident, even any mistake you have to pay. ומי אמר רבי
יוחנן הכי, umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi, did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
really say that? ואמר רבה בר בר חנה עובדא הוה קמיה דרבי
יוחנן, va'amar Rabba bar Bar Chana uvda hava kamei deRabbi Yochanan, there
was a story that came to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan בכנישתא דמעון,
bekhnishta deMaon, in the you know בית כנסת beit knesset of this
מעון, Maon, ואמר ליה זיל אייתי ראיה דממכית לתרנגולים ואפטרך. ve'amar lei
zil ayiti raya demamchis letarnigolim ve'eftarch.
So somebody came and said I gave this guy my chicken and
he was and he made it into a נבילה neveilah and and
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to the שוחט, shochet he said go
bring me proof that you have a דממכית, demamchis, like you know
you have you're a מומחה, mumcheh, that you have expertise. Show me
your siff- certificate that you have I didn't literally say certificate, you
know, but that you have expertise in שחיטה shchting chickens, and if
you had expertise then I'm going to assume that if something happened
it was clearly an accident, it wasn't negligence. So you see for
him if it you're an expert you are exempt. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בחינם כאן
בשכר, kan bechinam kan besachar, it depends if it's for free or
for fee or so that's like another issue we threw to these
two different settings. Number one, the more you're an expert the more
we assume it's not negligence. But now it's but the more you're
paid then maybe we'll buy into שמואל's idea. You know if you're
paying then there's no accidents then you have to be super careful
about everything. Okay, so he says if the guy is a so
when he said even if you're the world's best expert you're חייב,
chayav. that's if you're being paid. Okay, but if you're doing it
for free, okay, then if you're an expert then you are exempt.
Okay, yes.
I would think it would be the opposite. Why?
If I'm going to pay you, if I'm going to search out
the highest expert in the land and pay you.
Right, but that's not a function of whether you pay, meaning we're
as- you're right, you could assume if you're paying you found a
good person. But we're assuming this can be determined separately. Right.
No, no, I'm the
paying part, like
I might think that a lower level person should be allowed more
I should be allowed more negligence, right?
Well, you mean because I made the choice to give it to
this irresponsible person and that should be my fault, that should be
a פשיעה דניזק. pshia denizak. I was that I was wondering about.
Why don't you say that if I gave it to somebody who
wasn't an expert so why do you say look how negligent they
are, they don't even know fully they don't have full expertise and
they're still שחיטה shchting this animal. What happened to פשיעה דניזק? pshia
denizak? What happened to the fact that I was stupid enough to
give it to him? You know so he should
have said he should have
said this is beyond my level of expertise. Right, right, I agree.
And I but I was wondering exactly that question. Where is the
fault of the person who gave it to you know to have
agreed to give it to a person without full expertise? That's a
that is a good question.
Like, what if I'm giving you 300 things of wool or more,
thousands of em- like a person who whatever factory person, right, and
I give you like a ton of wool just to dye and
one comes back the wrong color. Is that like expected?
Yeah, those are really good questions and it parallels things that Dov
was saying before about let's say I tell I warn you about
the risks that are present. Right, so these things are not at
all worked out in the גמרא Gemara but they're very they're central
to put on the table. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, so okay, so for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan if you're
you're an expert you're חייב but only if you're being paid. Okay,
כי הא דאמר רבי זירא, ki ha de'amar Rabbi Zeira, like רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira said הרוצה שיתחייב לו טבח, arrotzeh sheyit-chayav lo tabbach,
if you want to make the butcher חייב if there's any mistake,
יקדים לו דינר, yakdim lo dinar,
make sure to pay him. Now the phrase יקדים לו דינר yakdim
lo dinar sounds pay him in advance, you know, I don't understand,
if I agreed to pay him does he have to get the
money in advance? But maybe the point is is that if you
don't pay him in advance he could always claim, oh, I thought
I was just doing it for free. Make sure it's a paid
arrangement. Okay, if you want to be able to be to collect
if there's if there's a problem. מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask you on
this. המוליך חטין לטחון ולא לתת, hamolich chitin litchon velo lasat, you
brought wheat to be ground to the guy who owned the mill,
and the person did not like, you know, the like removed the
husks, removed the shells, okay, that's לתת, lasat, I don't know what
the English word for that is, עשאן סובין assan subin and he
turned the stuff into bran or מורסן, morsan, another type of coarse
bread or or coarse grain, קמח לנחתום ועשאו פת ניפולין, kemach lenachtom
ve'asso pas nipolin, or you brought flour to the baker and he
made a bread that collapsed, right, you know it didn't stay puffed
up, it fell in, בהמה לטבח וניבלה, beheima letabbach venivla, or an
animal to a שוחט shochet. and he turned it into a נבילה,
neveilah, so all these things are you know mistakes on the per-
on the for the person who was hand- doing it, חייב מפני
שהוא כנושא שכר, chayav mipnei shehu k'nosei sachar, you're חייב because it's
like you're being paid. Now the fact that it says like you're
being paid seems to say Even without being paid, right, you have
because you're an expert and you're doing it professionally, you have that
level of responsibility and that level of care. And it's, and it's
just, and what it matter whether you're being paid or not? So
the problem is it says כנושא שכר. kenosei sachar. And according to
Rav Yochanan, you're only חייב when you're being paid. So the Gemara
says no, אימא מפני שהוא נושא שכר. eima mipnei shehu nosei sachar.
Take out the כ. kaf. It's not you're like being paid, it's
because you're being paid. Okay, and yes, you're only חייב if you're
being paid. Okay, now another story. ההוא מגרמיסא hahu magrumisa דאתא לקמיה
דרב. de'ata lekamei deRav. So a case of a מגרמיסא magrumisa which
is a complicated case, but it's basically a case of a שחיטה
shechitah where there was a question whether or not the שחיטה shechitah
was valid or not. It's a whole case that's debated about the
way the שחיטה shechitah was done and it's debated by the in
the גמרא Gemara whether or not it's a כשר kosher שחיטה. shechitah.
So a שוחט shochet did this and the case came to Rav.
So there were two questions that the owner wanted to know. A,
can I eat the meat? Is it כשר kosher or טרפה? treifah?
And B, if it's טרפה, treifah, can I get my can I
get the guy to pay me back for for my animal? Okay,
so what did Rav do? טרפיה, tarfei, he said the piece was
טרפה, treifah, ופטריה לטבח מלשלומי upatria letavach milishlumei and he said but
the butcher doesn't have to pay you for it. All right?
So so משלומי דמי mishlumei damei to pay the money. So פגעו
ביה רב כהנא ורב אסי בההוא גברא. pagu bei Rav Kahana veRav
Assi behahu gavra. Rav Kahana and Rav Assi bumped into this guy,
the owner of the cow. אמרו ליה עבד בך רב תרתי. amru
lei avad bach Rav tartei. Ah, Rav did you a he did
you a double. Okay, so what does it mean double? So it
sounds like he did two things bad to you. He told you
you couldn't eat the meat and you can't collect for you know
you can't collect from the שוחט. shochet So מאי תרתי? mai tartei?
What does it mean two things? אילימא תרתי לגריעותא, eileima tartei legreiuta,
two bad things. דיבאי ליה לאכשורי, deibai lei le'achshurei, first of all
he should have told you the meat was כשר kosher כרבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה. keRabbi Yossi beRabbi Yehuda. That's the position of Rabbi Yossi
beRabbi Yehuda in this type of a of a problem. Number one,
וטרפיה כרבנן, vetarfei keRabbanan, but he did wrong by you number one
that he made it a טרפה treifah following the רבנן. והינא כרבנן,
vehina keRabbanan, the second thing he did wrong with you is even
if he was going to פסקן pasken like the רבנן and say
it was טרפה, treifah, דיבאי ליה חיובי לטבחא, deibai lei chiyuvei letavacha,
he should have made the שוחט pay. So he did two things
wrong to you. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, that can't
be what they said to him. ומי שרי למימר כי האי גוונא?
umi shari lemeimar ki hai gavna? Is he permitted to make to
to critique a פסק psak like
that? דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא. וכשיצא, vechesheyatza, when a person
goes out of the deliberations of a court, one of the judges
leaves the court, right? And the court came out with a ruling
and he was in the minority. So nowadays, you know, the Supreme
Court, it issues a minority opinion. Okay, but but the court, בית
דין, Beis Din, has to speak in a single voice. So the
court ruled in a single voice, you're a minority one of the
minority opinion, you were overruled. When you leave the deliberations, לא יאמר,
lo yomar, don't go over to the litigant and say, you know,
אני מזכה וחבריי מחייבים, ani mezakeh vachaveirai mechayvim, I was trying to
say you were innocent, it was only everybody else that ruled you
were guilty. אבל מה אעשה שחבריי רבו עלי? aval mah e'eseh shechaveirai
rabu alai? But what could I do? They were the majority against
me. You're not allowed to say that. ועל זה נאמר, ve'al zeh
ne'emar, on this it is said הולך רכיל מגלה סוד, holech rachil
megaleh sod, one who goes as a talebearer and reveals secrets. Okay,
so you're not allowed to go out and violate the confidentiality of
the court, especially when the court is supposed to speak as one
body. Now there's a big problem applying that to here. What's the
problem applying that to here?
Who said they were part of the court? Who said they were
that they had deliberations among themselves and this was an a ruling
that emerged from the body, right? Maybe they just heard the פסק
psak and they were disagreed with the פסק. psak. What does that
mean? If, you know, David, you go to Dover and get a
פסק psak and he says, what? He said that to you? That's
not the הלכה. halacha. I'm allowed to say that, I'm allowed to
disagree with his פסק. psak. So it sounds like the גמרא Gemara
feels that they were part of the deliberations. But even if they
were part of the deliberations, you would think that there's a difference
between if it's a body of a בית דין Beis Din that
comes out with a unified ruling or if, you know, we're שמוזינג
schmoozing in הלכה halacha and then you פסקן pasken somewhere and I
was part of the conversation but I disagree with your פסק. psak.
It's very strange, I feel, that the גמרא Gemara feels that they
were not allowed to say this. Unless the גמרא Gemara really imagines
that this was a בית דין, Beis Din, but who needs a
בית דין Beis Din to פסקן pasken a כשרות kashrus case? You
know, so I really don't get it. You're allowed to disagree with
פסקים. psakim. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara says they could not have
been criticizing Rav like that. אלא תרתי למעליותא, ela tartei lema'alyuta, no,
they were saying the opposite. Rav did you a double good. You
should be happy with Rav's פסק. psak. He did two good things
for you. Why did he do two good things for you? Number
one, לא אוכלך ספק איסורא, lo achlach sefek issura, he didn't make
you eat this meat that according to many is טרפה. treifah. He's
saving you from that ritual איסור. issur. And number two, מנחך מספק
גזילה, manachach misfek gezeila, and he didn't make and he didn't tell
the guy to pay. Why would it be a ספק גזילה? sefek
gezeila? Because you understand, if the meat was כשר, kosher, he wouldn't
have to pay you. So Rav is saying don't eat it לחומרא,
lechumra, it's not ודאי vadai טרפה. treifah. It might be טרפה, treifah,
so don't eat it. But since it might be כשר, kosher, you
can't make the שוחט pay. So look how good Rav is doing
to you. He's saving you from the איסור issur of טרפה treifah
and he's saving you from the איסור issur of גזילה. gezeila. Okay,
now of course you could say that if the accepted פסק psak
in this case is to say it's אסור. assur. Even if the
accepted פסק *psak* in this case is to say it's אסור *assur*,
even if the accepted פסק *psak* says to say it's אסור מספק
*assur mi-safek*, then the שוחט *shochet* still made a mistake that led
to a meat that couldn't be eaten. You know, but but maybe
not, maybe since there are other people that say the meat is
כשר *kosher*, you know and if you go to them they would
say it's כשר *kosher*, so you can't make the שוחט *shochet* pay,
and רבא *Rava* is sort of saying you gotta play it safe
in both ways. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
Why don't you make the שוחט *shochet* pay?
Because it might be כשר *kosher*.
It might be כשר *kosher*.
Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay, איתמר *itmar*.
Now we're going to switch to a case of not שחיטה *shechita*
where there's an obvious damage to the object. The object, the food
is now a piece of נבילה *neveila*, and we're going to deal
with somebody who gives you bad professional advice. Okay? Like your lawyer
gives you bad professional advice. But here it's going to be a
money changer.
איתמר *itmar* goes and re-quotes something that's already...
No, it's a new thing.
איתמר *itmar* is always a new thing. תניא *tanya* is always a
new thing. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, גופא *gufa* or or אמר מר *Amar Mar* is going back.
Okay. איתמר *itmar*, המראה דינר לשולחני *hamarei dinar leshulchani*,
somebody shows a coin to a money exchanger, which basically is,
Joe here wants to buy
my cow, and he gives me some ten gold coins, but I'm
not sure that these gold coins are are they authentic, are they
forgeries, do they have the full amount of weight, will other merchants
accept them, they're a little damaged. So I go over to David
and I say, David, here are the coins. Are these coins like
acceptable currency? And David says, yeah, they're fine. And I accept it
from Joe, I sell him my cow, and then I try to
use the coins in a store and they get rejected. Can I
go to David and say, David, you made me accept this currency
which isn't good, I want you to pay me back. Okay? So
I'm going to sue you. You didn't damage anything, but your bad
professional advice caused me a loss. All right? So איתמר *itmar*, המראה
דינר לשולחני *hamarei dinar leshulchani*, you show a coin to a money
trader, ונמצא רע *ve-nimtza ra*, and it turns out that it's a
non-acceptable coin when you then try to spend it. תני חדא *tani
chada*, אומן פטור הדיוט חייב *uman patur hedyot chayav*. So we have
one that says the difference again between an expert and a non-expert.
An expert is exempt. Every now and then people will make mistakes;
it's seen as not a negligence. But a הדיוט *hedyot* is חייב
*chayav*. ותניא אידך *tanya idach*, בין אומן בין הדיוט חייב *bein uman
bein hedyot chayav*. And another one says, no, even an אומן *uman*
is חייב *chayav*. So this seems to be the debate before: Do
we assume that the mistakes that an expert makes have are negligent
or not, have a degree of negligence? Okay? So this is a
debate whether an... Everybody agrees a הדיוט *hedyot* is חייב *chayav*. The
question is is an אומן *uman* חייב *chayav*? אמר רב פפא *Amar
Rav Pappa*, כי תניא אומן פטור *ki tanya uman patur*, now when
do we say an אומן *uman* was exempt? כגון דנכו ואיסר *kegon
Danku ve-Issur*, like these two money traders, דנכו *Danku* and איסר *Issur*,
they have nothing left to learn. Okay, they are the top of
their field. Okay, they you cannot say to them that they should
have known some more fact or had some skill that they didn't
have. So that's a case where I'll say because you're such an
אומן *uman* there's no negligence. Okay? אלא במאי *ella be-mai*? So the
גמרא gemara, *Gemara* says if that's true, if they were so knowledgeable,
then what how did they make a mistake? אלא במאי טעו *ella
be-mai ta'u*? What was the mistake they made if it wasn't that
there was some information they didn't know? טעו בסיכתא חדתא *ta'u be-sikta
chadta*. Now they made a mistake that there was just today new
coins were minted and somehow the old coins were now less valuable,
but somehow that word didn't get to them yet. Now you could
say, hey, if that's your business and you're the experts in the
field, you should be knowing before anybody else when the new coins
are being minted. But whatever it is, the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says
that they are total experts and they just didn't have a new
piece of data which had just come out. So with that we
can understand that's a legitimate, that's like an אונס *ones*. Okay? But
basically he's saying fundamentally even an אומן *uman* is חייב *chayav*. If
there's any more, you know, you know, you know,
anything that is a hair shy of being perfect, you know, that's
considered to be your fault and you're חייב *chayav*. דההיא שעתא דנפקי
מצותא דסיכתא *de-hahu sha'ata de-nafki mitzuta de-sikta* and it was at that
moment that the new coin was just minted and that's why they
made the mistake. Okay, but basically other than the world's best experts,
okay, this is basically the שמואל *Shmuel* position that even an אומן
*uman* is חייב *chayav*. ההיא איתתא *ha-hi itteta*, there was a woman
דאחזיא דינרא לרבי חייא *de-achzaya dinara le-Rabbi Chiyya*, she showed her דינר
*dinar* that somebody was paying her to רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Rabbi
Chiyya* and said can I accept this coin? So אמר לה *Amar
lah*, he said מעליא הוא *ma'alya hu*, yes it's a good coin
you can accept it. למחר אתאי לקמיה ואמרה *le-machar atayei lekamei ve-amra*,
the next day she came to him and said לה *leh*, and
she said to him, אחזיתיה ואמרו לי בישא הוא *achziteih ve-amru li
bisha hu*, I showed it to the person to a storekeeper, you
know, somebody I wanted to use it for with, and they tell
me it was a bad coin, ולא קא נפיק לי *velo ka
nafik li*, and he wouldn't accept it from me. So אמר ליה
לרב *Amar leih le-Rav*, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Rabbi Chiyya* said
to רב *Rav*, who was like his attendant or his student, זיל
חלפיה ניהלה *zil chalfeih nihalah*, fine, go ahead, take the coin, give
her another one in exchange. Okay, basically he was willing to pay
for the loss. וכתוב אפנקסי *ve-chtov apinkasi*, and write in my notebook,
דין עסק ביש *dein esek bish*, this was like it's a write-off.
You know, this was a bad deal. This was a bad business.
Now רב *Rav* says it was a bad business
because רב *Rav*... רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
bottom of the very last lines: שחורא היא שסחקי חנם אני מפסיד
שלא היה לי לראותה *sechora hi she-isaki chinam ani mafsid shelo hayah
li li-rotah*. Like what was I doing getting involved in looking at
somebody's coins? I could have said you know what go show that
to the money changer, I'm in the middle of teaching the שיעור
here. Okay? So I thought I was doing somebody a טובה, tovah,
and now by the way, it shows he's a הדיוט, right? This
might be a case of a הדיוט and that's why he's חייב.
The אומן is still a debated issue. Okay. ומאי שנא דנכו ואיסור
דפטירי, Umai shna Danku v'Issar de'ptiri,
excuse me, I just made a mistake. He wasn't a הדיוט. Right,
the next line in the גמרא Gemara actually says that רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya was actually an expert. Okay? So רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
apparently was an expert coin trader. So if he's an expert coin
trader, why is he liable? So the גמרא says ומאי שנא דנכו
ואיסור דפטירי, Umai shna Danku v'Issar de'ptiri, if we said top-level experts
are exempt, משום דלא צריכי למיגמר, mishum d'lo tzrichi l'migmar,
because there's nothing left for them to learn, so we really do
assume it's a freak case. So the גמרא says רבי חייא apparently
that was his business and he also was an expert. רבי חייא
נמי לאו למיגמר קא בעי. Rabbi Chiya nami lav l'migmar ka ba'ei.
רבי חייא also didn't have anything to learn about the trade, meaning
not that he didn't have anything to learn about תורה. Torah. He
didn't have anything left to learn about the trade. Apparently he was
a real expert in this, a total top-level expert. So why was
he liable? So the גמרא says רבי חייא לפנים משורת הדין הוא
דעבד. Rabbi Chiya lifnim mishurat hadin hu de'avid. You're right. Really, look,
this lady was complaining and saying it's your fault. Technically he was
exempt, but he didn't want anybody to have any טענות tainos against
him. And he therefore was doing it and that's maybe why he
said this is a write-off. It's a write-off because I really shouldn't
have to pay her, but I don't want her to be upset,
you know? I did indirectly cause her loss, even though it wasn't
my fault. Fine, let's just reimburse her. He went beyond the letter
of the law. By the way, interesting insight: why is the Hebrew
expression of beyond the letter of the law לפנים משורת הדין? lifnim
mishurat hadin? Inside the law. Right? You want everybody should be operating
within the law. Right? It's like beyond, so why is it the
opposite expression? So the idea is that in, I think this goes
back also, you know, to
Greek thought as well, right? If this is you, you're
the
human being, okay? And this is the world of the sphere of
possible activities that you can be doing in the world, the law
conscripts that, conscribes, anyway, inscribes,
anyway, the law restricts it. The law says no, no, you can't
do, you can't be מזיק, no, but I would know what does
it mean to, I know פשר, posher, but it's also to like
limit, anyway, whatever, doesn't matter. Anyway, you can't be מזיק, you can't
be גוזל, gozel, you can't cheat, you can't do whatever. The law
draws a fence around you and says these are the limits, this
is the limit of your acceptable activity. So if you do beyond
what the law is demanding, you're operating לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishurat
hadin, right?
So you're operating, you know, if you think about it, right? So
you understand? So I mean, because normally we think about acting in
a
positive way rather than like an עשה aseh versus a לא תעשה.
lo ta'aseh. But the idea here is, you know, you're not, you,
this is the extent of permission the law gives you. The law
gives you the permission to give this ruling and not have to
pay. But you're, you know, you're further, you know,
constricting your sphere of activity. So that's the phrase לפנים משורת הדין.
lifnim mishurat hadin. Okay, anyway, so he acted לפנים משורת הדין הוא
דעבד. lifnim mishurat hadin hu de'avid. כדתניא רב יוסף, Kidetanya Rav Yosef,
like רב יוסף Rav Yosef taught, והודעת להם V'hodata lahem זה בית
חייהם. zeh beit chayeihem. So, you know, and this is by the
whole, this is so amazing, right? Here it is יתרו Yitro giving
advice to משה Moshe before מתן תורה. Matan Torah. I mean, you
got to just think for a moment about the audacity of that
whole thing. God's about to give the, you know, the direct divine
revelation from heaven, and here beforehand, you know, יתרו Yitro is this
non-Jew is telling משה Moshe about how to sort of arrange his
whole court system. And not only that, but חזל Chazal read into
יתרו's Yitro advice that יתרו Yitro is sort of telling משה Moshe
that it's not
all
about the law. There are parts of human responsibility that are not
defined totally by הלכה. halacha. Okay? So והודעת להם, V'hodata lahem, you
should tell them, זה בית חייהם, zeh beit chayeihem, this is their
house of life. What does that mean? רשי Rashi says it means,
רשי says תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. Other ways רשי says it means
no, that it means the responsibility that people have to learn a
trade, which fits in also well here. Okay? So it's, you know,
you have to teach a trade. את הדרך, Et haderech, you should
inform them the path, זו גמילות חסדים. zu gemilut chasadim. It's not
just your legal responsibilities. You have to do acts of kindness beyond
your legal responsibilities. ילכו, Yelchu, that they should walk, זו ביקור חולים.
zu bikur cholim. גמרא says isn't that a type of גמילות חסדים?
gemilut chasadim? So fine, but whatever.
בה, Bah, the path they should go in it, זה קבורה, zeh
kvurah, even a type of a, you know, what the גמרא calls
חסד של אמת, chesed shel emet, something that there's
no hope for getting compensated for, right? You know, or getting any
type of, you know, not just compensated, you know, any reciprocity for,
you know, burying a dead body. את המעשה, Et hama'aseh, the act,
זה הדין. zeh hadin. Obviously they have to do the law. But...
אשר יעשון *Asher yaasun*,
that they should do, זו לפנים משורת הדין *zu lifnim mishuras hadin*.
Don't just do the law, go beyond or within the letter of
the law, go beyond the letter of the law and act presumably
understood to be the spirit of the law even if not what
the law strictly demands. So yes, he did not have to reimburse,
but he wanted to do the right thing. Now by the way,
תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* has a great question. תוספות Tosafoses *Tosfos* says
that
another גמרא *Gemara* has a case, I mentioned before about workers that
trip and they break something etc. So there's a גמרא *Gemara* in
בבא מציעא *Bava Metzia* that had a case of workers that tripped
and they broke something and they were liable to pay and the-
whoever it was, the rabbi didn't want to pay them, רבה בר
בר חנה *Rabba bar bar Channah*, so he basically he took their
clothes or he took their coats and he was holding onto it
until they would reimburse him for his wine and the- whoever it
was he went to פסקן pasken *pasken* says no, they're actually exempt.
So he said is that the הלכה halacha *halacha*? He says so
he said no, it's not the הלכה *halacha* but he says he
says למען תלך בדרך טובים *lemaan telech bederech tovim*. You should do
the right thing even if it's not the הלכה *halacha*. And then
the workers said we're starving, we worked the whole day. So he
says pay them. He says that's the הלכה *halacha*? He says no
you know he says וארחות צדיקים תשמור *ve'orchos tzaddikim tishmor*. Do the
right thing. So תוספות *Tosfos* says why didn't it say לפנים משורת
הדין *lifnim mishuras hadin*? So this is a very interesting question. When
is it a complete act of חסד *chessed* and when is it
like the spirit of the law but not the letter of the
law? So one thing that תוספות *Tosfos* suggests is that that here
you were getting basically taking an exemption that would not normally apply.
Most people would have to reimburse. Because you were an expert, you
wouldn't. So you know what? You're entitled to the exemption. Legally you're
entitled to the exemption but do the right thing, don't claim the
exemption. Okay so that's a way of saying like that's a לפנים
משורת הדין *lifnim mishuras hadin*. That's different than saying like do an
act of צדקה *tzedaka*, an act of חסד *chessed* etc. Just don't-
you're entitled to it but don't claim. And תוספות *Tosfos* has other
ways of distinguishing but it raises the interesting question of when is
it sort of this moral mandate of the spirit of the law
and when is it something that's beyond, you know, above and beyond.
All right so now
the
גמרא *Gemara* continues. ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* אחוי ליה דינרא לרבי אלעזר
*achvei lei dinra le-Rabbi Elazar*. ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* showed a דינרא
*dinra* to רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*. אמר מאי ניהו *Amar mai nihu*?
It's good. אמר ליה חזי דעלך קסמיכנא *Amar lei chazi de'alach kasamichna*.
Note that I am relying on you. Okay? If something goes wrong
I'm going to come back and ask you to compensate me. אמר
ליה *Amar lei* so he said back אם קסמכת עלי מאי למימרא
*im kasamichat alai mai lememra*? It's nice to know you're relying on
me but what do you think you're going to get out of
that? You think you want me to pay you if something goes
wrong? ואי משתכח בישא בעינא לחלוופי לך *Ve'im mishtakach bisha beina lachlufei
lach*? You think that if it's a bad coin I'm going to
have to exchange it for you because you're saying that you're relying
on me? ואתו דאמרית רב מאיר הוא דדן דינא דגרמי *Va'atu de'amrit
Reb Meir hu de'dan dina degarmi*. Now we get to a question.
Until now we've been dealing with the negligence of the אומן *uman*
but what we haven't been dealing with is that there's nothing damaged
here. It's one thing if I'm negligent and I break your box
or I'm negligent and I turn your בהמה *beheima* into נבילה *neveila*.
I didn't damage anything. What are you going to make me pay
for? Indirectly I caused you a loss. My bad advice got you
to accept this and indirectly caused- nothing was damaged. I'm not- right?
So what is that? That's גרמא grama *grama*. Okay fine I was
negligent I caused you a loss, go make
me- go make me pay, that's גרמא Grama *grama*. So he says
one minute, you want me to pay? You're the one who says
that the only reason you pay by this case of the coin
and the bad professional advice is according to רב מאיר *Reb Meir*
who דן דינא דגרמי *dan dina degarmi*. Okay רב מאיר *Reb Meir*
who makes people pay in certain cases of גרמא Grama *grama*. Okay?
So that's why you would have to pay. You know you can
understand that right? It's the difference between bad legal advice and you
know the auto mechanic or the- who ruins the car or the
doctor who kills the patient you know? But but yes, but bad
business advice is a גרמא grama. *grama*. It's not a direct act
of מזיק *mazik*. So you say that that's- the idea that you
would have to pay for that follows רב מאיר דדן דינא דגרמי
*Reb Meir de-dan dina degarmi*. מאי לאו רב מאיר ולא סבירא לן
כותיה *Mai lav Reb Meir velo sevira lan kavateih*? Shouldn't I infer
from that that that's only a רב מאיר *Reb Meir* position and
that's not our פסק *psak*? Our פסק *psak* is you don't have
to pay that. אמר ליה לא רב מאיר וסבירא לן כותיה *Amar
lei lo, Reb Meir usevira lan kavateih*. No, it is רב מאיר
*Reb Meir* and that is how we פסקן *pasken*. We do פסקן
*pasken* דינא דגרמי *dina degarmi*. So this is important right if you
remember just two or three days ago רבה *Rabba* had all these
crazy cases about flattening a coin etc. and finally the גמרא *Gemara*
pushed back and said according to רב מאיר *Reb Meir* you'd have
to pay at least for some of those. And here too comes
רב מאיר *Reb Meir* to close a gap. There are cases of
גרמא grammas *grama* you may be exempt but there are cases where
there's real fault and liability and you know and we exactly to
figure out what's גרמי garmi. *garmi* and what's גרמא Grammas *grama* is
major major discussions in the ראשונים rishonim *Rishonim*. But nevertheless this comes
to to close the gap. And it is רב מאיר *Reb Meir*
and you do pay if you are negligent and we פסקן *pasken*
this way. Now the גמרא *Gemara* says האי רבי מאיר *Hai Rabbi
Meir*, which רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* is it? Before we were trying
to figure out, you know, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* is really like
tough-going. You slip, it's negligence. I don't care you're an expert, any
slip, not an accident. Number two, I don't care if it's גרמא
*grama*, if you're enough to blame, it's גרמי garmi, *garmi* you pay.
Okay, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* really, you know, is a has a
consistent position here of making sure that people get compensated for their
losses. Okay, so האי רבי מאיר *Hai Rabbi Meir*. Which רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir*? אילימא רבי מאיר דתנן *Ileima Rabbi Meir detnan*, the following
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. דן את הדין זיכה את החייב חייב את
הזכאי טימא את הטהור טיהר את הטמא מה שעשה עשוי וישלם מביתו
*Dan et hadin zika et hachayav chiyav et hazakai tima et hatahor
tihar et hatame ma she'asa asuy veyeshalem mibeito*. So you're a פוסק
*posek*, and you basically said, you know, this guy who really owes
a hundred dollars, you said he was exempt. Or the guy who
was who was exempt, you said he had to pay the hundred
dollars. Or grain that was טמא *tame*, you said was טהור *tahor*.
טהור *tahor*, you said was טמא *tame*. Okay, now the point is,
a lot of those cases you could say just reverse it once
you find out you made a mistake. But there are cases that
then aren't reversible. You mixed the grain that was believed to be
טהור *tahor* with other טהור *tahor* grain. Now you find out it's
טמא *tame*, all the טהור *tahor* grain you mixed it with is
now טמא *tame*. Okay, the guy you said was חייב *chayav* paid
the money and the other guy who took the money is nowhere
to be found to give the money back, you know? So you
basically made a פסק *psak*, it caused a loss, it can't be
reversed. Okay, this is like legal malpractice, not legal as the lawyer,
legal as the judge, judicial malpractice, I guess. Okay, so can you
get your money back? Now that the guy admits that he made
a wrong פסק *psak*. Okay, so the הלכה *halacha* is מה שעשה
עשוי *ma she'asa asuy*, the פסק *psak* cannot be reversed, וישלם מביתו
*veyeshalem mibeito*, and you have to pay if you gave the wrong
פסק *psak*. Okay, now there, you should say if anything first of
all it's complete גרמא *grama*, right? Cause I didn't like I didn't
do anything to the thing, like if you went ahead and paid
the guy, I didn't take the money out of your hand and
pay the guy. It's גרמא *grama*. Not only is it גרמא *grama*,
but like you know, talk about an idea of an expert and
you know, being exempt as an expert and so on. You would
hope that anybody who is a דיין *dayan* would be an expert.
Not necessarily, you know, we say that he you know, you could
even the there are things that even a הדיוט *hedyot* could דן
*dan* for. There's you know, all sorts like there's the whole joke
about what do you call the doctor who graduated you know the
guy graduated bottom of his med class in medical school? Doctor, right?
So so not everybody is an expert who's in the field. Anyway,
so here you're paying. Okay, so is this seems to be סתם
משנה mishna, רבי מאיר *stam mishna Rabbi Meir*? So maybe this is
the רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* of דינא דגרמי *dina d'garmi*? It's only
indirect and you're paying. Here it is, דינא דגרמי *dina d'garmi*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says no, הא איתמר עלה אמר רבי אילא אמר
רב והוא שנטל ונתן ביד *ha itmar alah amar Rabbi Ila amar
Rav vehu shenatal venatan beyad*. It's not you gave a פסק *psak*
and the guy went and he paid the other guy. You gave
a פסק *psak* and you went and you took the money out
of ראובן *Reuven's* pocket and handed it to שמעון *Shimon* to show
how definite you were about your פסק *psak*. Okay, it's like what
are you know, it's very interesting. Like sometimes because people are like
uncertain they overcompensate, you know? So you wanted to show how certain
you were about your פסק *psak*, you ripped the money from his
hand, you gave it to his hand, so you're a מזיק בידיים
*mazik beyadayim* now. It's not a it's not a גרמא *grama*. אלא
הא רבי מאיר *ela ha Rabbi Meir*. So you can't prove it
from that case. Fine, let's try this case. דתנן *detnan*, another משנה
*mishna*, and סתם משנה רבי מאיר *stam mishna Rabbi Meir*. צבעו אדום
וצבעו שחור שחור צבעו אדום *tzevalo adom utzevalo shachor shachor tzevalo adom*.
רבי מאיר אומר נותן לו דמי צמרו *Rabbi Meir omer noten lo
dmei tzemaro*, you pay him. So you see, so oh look, you
caused a loss and you're paying. So there's an obvious answer. התם
קעביד בידיים *hasam ka'avid beyadayim*. What are you talking about? That isn't
גרמא *grama*, that's direct. So תוספות *Tosafos* says what was the הוה
אמינא *hava amina*? So תוספות *Tosafos* the הוה אמינא *hava amina* is
it took a few minutes after you put it in the pot
for it to absorb the dye. So maybe you see that as
a little bit of indirect. But nevertheless, the גמרא *Gemara's* rejecting that.
The גמרא *Gemara* says no, that's direct. אלא הא רבי מאיר *ela
ha Rabbi Meir*, the following רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, דתנן *detnan*. המסכך
את גפנו על גבי תבואתו של חבירו *hamasech et gefano al gabei
tevu'ato shel chaveiro*. You go ahead and you take your vine and
you have it hang over your friend's wheat and you're going to
make כלאים kilayim *kilayim*. Okay, הרי זה קידש *harei ze kidesh*, it's
the word is קידש *kidesh*, but it doesn't mean holy, it means
you made it into כלאים kilayim *kilayim*, וחייב *vechayav*, and you have
to pay your friend for now making his wheat not kosher. So
you see there also that's a גרמא *grama*. So גמרא *Gemara* says
it's not a גרמא *grama*, התם נמי קעביד בידיים *hasam nami ka'avid
beyadayim*, you're doing it directly. So תוספות *Tosafos* again says what was
the הוה אמינא *hava amina*? So here was the הוה אמינא *hava
amina*. The הוה אמינא *hava amina* is it doesn't become כלאים kilayim.
*kilayim* at the second you do it. Only after they grow together
for a little while. So the growing happens afterwards. But the גמרא
*Gemara* says give me a break, that is not the same degree
of גרמא *grama* as giving somebody's advice and them acting on your
advice, you know? That is you did a direct act and this
naturally then then emerge from your direct act. Okay, you cannot prove
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* from that case. אלא הא רבי מאיר *ela
ha Rabbi Meir*, the following רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, דתניא *detanya*. מחיצת
הכרם שנפרצה *mechitzat hakerem shenipretza*, another כלאים kilayim *kilayim* case. You have
a wall that's between a vineyard and a wheat field. Even if
they're right next to each other, if there's a a separator there,
it's not כלאים kilayim *kilayim*. Now the wall fell down. Now it
is כלאים *kilayim*. אומר לו גדור *omer lo gedor*, you say to
him build up the wall, he builds it up again. נפרצה *nipretza*,
fell down again. אומר אמרו לו גדור, you say build it up
again. נתייאש ממנה ולא גדר Nitya'esh mimena velo gadar and the guy
says forget it, I'm not going to keep on rebuilding this wall.
Okay, now as long as he is trying to prevent it from
being כלאים and build the wall, it doesn't become כלאים even if
they're growing together. Okay, תוספות asks why, but basically because the תורה
Torah says כרמך לא תזרע כלאים. Karmeka lo tizra kilayim. It has
to be like you're planting it, like you will it. As long
as you're trying to prevent it, it's not. But as soon as
you've said forget it, I'm not going to bother, and then they
continue to grow together, it's כלאים. So how did it become כלאים
here? Not by an action you did, but by an inaction. And
the הלכה is הרי זה קידש וחייב באחריותו. harei ze kidesh vechayav
be'achrayuto. It is כלאים and you have to pay. You have to
pay the other guy for ruining his wheat. So there's an interesting
question, why is it your fault, your responsibility, not the other guy's?
But that's not our issue. The point is you were completely passive,
it became, the wheat became ruined due to your passivity, passive inaction,
and nevertheless, because you're to blame, you have to pay. So it's
a משנה, we assume it's רבי מאיר, and this is the principle
that רבי מאיר does דיני דגרמי dinei degarmi and we פסקן like
that, and that closes the gap for things like flattening the coins
that we talked about a while ago, or hitting a guy's hand
and it's flying into the ocean, and it closes the gap for
giving, it opens up a whole field of legal malpractice. You are
now liable if you gave bad professional advice. And as I mentioned
before, the ראשונים rishonim have long discussions, interestingly, all of these תוספות
are not discussing the parameters of גרמי. garmi They're discussing other related,
sort of tangential issues. But the key issue of our גמרא, what
exactly defines גרמא versus גרמי, garmi. what's the line between the two
of them? Right, that's like major, major discussions in the ראשונים because
the גמרא never fully, fully clarifies.
גרמא and גרמי are two different terms?
גרמא you're exempt from. רבי מאיר is not מחייב mechayev all גרמא.
He's מחייב mechayev certain types of גרמא which are high degree of
causation, high degree of what exactly are the parameters? It's not clear.
But let's just make it a little tautologous statement. גרמא that you
should be paying for, those are גרמי. Okay, so grammatically like נזמי?
nazmi?
Maybe. Yeah, some say the יוד yod makes it mean that you're
more, yeah, some question what the יוד yod is meant to mean
there. Yeah. Okay. All right.
גמרא also could you explain...